[Music]
Welcome to Business Central launch
edition of 2025 release wave 2. This
session is about the new things we did
for data analysis.
Did you know that more than 70% of all
Business Central customers use data
analysis, also known as analysis mode?
You take a list page or query into
analysis mode and now you can kind of
pivot and and group data kind of a a
report but it's not a report it's just
ad hoc analysis.
The uh this feature helps so many
scenarios uh with within analytics and
uh we even added a great co-pilot
experience a couple of releases back so
that you can also use natural language
to describe what you want. And uh
because of this the popularity, we
actually wanted to give you uh a few
productivity improvements and we also
have um also some improvements for the
analysis assist copilot so that
hopefully this can unlock even more
scenarios that help you as a customer
get data driven. So let's go into
business central and see analysis assist
copilot the new features and the the two
more improvements that um that we added.
So here I have opened the sales lines
list page and if I take this into
analysis mode then you have the data
analysis tool that you probably already
use if you're among the 70% of
customers.
Now um let's try to create a new
analysis and uh I will just
ask my co-pilot to summarize my sales.
These are sales lines. Um and I would
like quantity and amount. I don't I just
call it Q and amount probably. Okay. And
I want to group this by location name.
Now in the sales line list here we only
have location code. So location name is
something that is in a different table
somewhere from another part of Business
Central linked to the sales lines. So uh
let's see what Copilot uh can do here
and uh let's see. So generate and just
wait for that to chew on my prompt and
get back to me. Let's see what it comes
up with. Here we go. So it comes up with
location code. Now I actually wanted it
to have location name. So let's just ask
copilot uh please use location
name and not location code
and see if we get what we want.
Bingo. So notice over here
that we're actually getting our location
name uh because the copilot can traverse
the data model and see that it can join
to somewhere else where it can find
location code um and then get the name
from there. So we'll just keep this
um analysis location name sales salary
that's summary that's fine. Um, and
that's actually what I wanted. So that's
the first demo. So we have now ability
for analysis assist to also add fields
from tables that are related to what
you're using here. That feature if you
want to do it yourself is the add
columns from. So C-pilot can kind of use
this feature that we added in the last
release. So let's go back to our
analysis. One new thing is a little info
here. This is because whenever you do
that uh adding data from other tables or
if you have a lot of data or if you're
analyzing a query object or data from a
query object, we switch the data loading
in analysis mode from what we call
client side where we just load
everything in the browser to server side
where we load things on demand. And
that's when you do that there are few
things we you can't do such as flow
fields things that are calculated uh
that cannot be calculated on the
database. Um and that is the message you
see here. So if you have this uh you you
would you know that you are in that uh
serverside mode. One of the things you
could not do in serverside mode until
this release is pivoting on date
hierarchy um date hierarchy fields. So
what does that mean? Date hierarchy
fields. Well, um over here in the column
section, uh whenever we have things that
are related to dates, here is the
shipment date. Um we always like since
the beginning of this feature calculate
a hierarchy of year, quarter, month um
and that makes it much easier to do
analysis based on calendar. However, in
um in this serverside mode, you could
not pivot on quarter, month um and year
until now. So, let's try to take this
analysis into pivot mode. There we go.
And that opens up the new columns labels
menu. And now I can uh maybe put in the
quarter and drag that in here. And now I
pivot on quarter. We also the third
feature I wanted to show you is that we
have some productivity improvements on
the menu here. So let's take the date
month. If I right click on this, you
have new menu items here. So I can add
shipment date month to the labels. So I
don't have to drag it. I can also use my
like the right click. Then you see the
the month is happening in here. Another
thing is if I choose let's say type a
new field here I can then rightclick
here and uh group ungroup. So actually
let me just get rid of pivot mode here.
Uh choose type again. I right click on
this um and I can um group or ungroup uh
from the row groups. So let's say you
can see type is down here. I can either
remove it classically like this or I can
choose the new ungroup action. And if I
choose this then I'm ungrouping.
Another uh small productivity feature is
scroll t this into view. So any field if
let's say that I move the type to uh
somewhere where I can't see it in my on
my screen here. So type is now hidden.
If I then right click on type, I can
scroll this into view by choosing this
action. And now I I get uh to see my
type column. You can see the the the
scroll bar here is then kind of showing
type. So those are the three new
features in data analysis. The first one
is that copilot analysis assists can add
fields from related tables. The second
is that in pivot mode when you're in
server side, we support the pivoting on
these calendar fields um in the
hierarchy. And the third was these small
um right-click menus. So you can also
you don't have to drag and drop so much.
If you just want to use uh those you can
do that. So get away from the computer
and get to learn this by using these two
resources in Microsoft Learn. There's a
link here to aka/ms/bc
analytics. That's the landing page for
everything. So that's actually taking
you to the landing page for everything
analytics. Here you need to navigate to
ad hoc analysis and in that menu there
are two articles of interest. The first
article is about using data analysis
feature as such. So how does everything
work? If you tried maybe actually go
there and browse it. There might be
functionality that you didn't know
existed. I've had a lot of partner
conversations or customers where they
said, "Oh, I never knew that I could
whatever it is." So, browse that. The
second link is equally important. Those
are uh landing pages for different
functional areas of business central
where we have documented scenarios uh
for for data analysis that you can get
inspired in case you're not uh
completely if you're a bit new to this
um this feature. Um maybe there's some
um inspiration in finance or sales or
purchasing and so on. So you can kind of
see oh that's clever. If I take this
page into analysis mode and do this, I
can analyze this. And you can even take
those descriptions because they are
actually uh point one 23 like go here,
do this, do this. Uh most of these
examples you can just copy that directly
from the documentation article, plug it
into data to the analysis assist copilot
and in many cases it will just create
the an analysis tab directly for you. So
that's it. Before you go, if you're not
familiar with our LinkedIn profile, do
check this aka.ms/bc
LinkedIn. Follow us there. This is where
we have almost daily or weekly news on
things all things happening uh on
Business Central as seen from our
product group in engineering.
You're watching this on YouTube. So So
maybe you already know our YouTube
channel. If you do not then aka.ms/bc
YouTube. This takes you to our channel.
You should probably follow us there. We
put in small uh what's new co-pilot and
AI news or videos, tips and tricks, deep
dives and so on. Um so YouTube is
definitely a place where you can learn
much much more about all things Business
Central.
And if that's not enough, um,
aka.ms/bcall
is a landing page for all the aka links
that exists, I think, for partners. So,
bookmark that and you'll have the one
AKA link to rule them all. If you're a
Business Central partner and if you're
not yet on Yammer, please uh go there
with our AK link BC AK.msbc
Yammer. This is where everything
discussions, questions, everything
around business central is happening
there and it's a closed forum. No
customers uh are are there. You can like
speak freely on of of everything if
you're a customer. Sorry about that. Uh
office hours, this the last link
aka.ms/bc
office hours is our calendar for office
hours. We do office hour calls almost
once every month on topics that relate
to Business Central in the future. Those
are open both for customers and
partners. So go check that out and make
sure that you join our office hours. And
with that, thanks a lot for watching and
I hope you get a great Business Central
launch um edition. Thanks.